<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Protection proclaimed (through the loving kindness of God in the present government) to the three nations of England, Scotland, and Ireland: wherein the government established, in the Lord Protector and his council, is proved to be of divine institution; and the great stumbling-block of thousands of Christians (in regard of his title) removed; proving it to be none other than what hath been given to those whom God hath made instrumental for his peoples deliverance of old. / Written to satisfie unsatisfied consciences, by John Moore, a well-wisher to the peace of our English Jerusalem.</title>
            <author>Moore, John, of Wechicombe, near Dunster, Somerset.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2562</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E860_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206643</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865760</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865760</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118011</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89259)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118011)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 130:E860[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Protection proclaimed (through the loving kindness of God in the present government) to the three nations of England, Scotland, and Ireland: wherein the government established, in the Lord Protector and his council, is proved to be of divine institution; and the great stumbling-block of thousands of Christians (in regard of his title) removed; proving it to be none other than what hath been given to those whom God hath made instrumental for his peoples deliverance of old. / Written to satisfie unsatisfied consciences, by John Moore, a well-wisher to the peace of our English Jerusalem.</title>
                  <author>Moore, John, of Wechicombe, near Dunster, Somerset.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for Henry Fletcher, at the three Cups in Paul's Church-yard, neer the west-end.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656 [i.e. 1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>It appears that Thomason received his copy before 1656.</note>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "Nouemb 22. 1655", the 6 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:118011:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Protection proclaimed (through the loving kindneſs of God in the preſent Government) to the three Nations of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> WHEREIN The GOVERNMENT Eſtabliſhed, in the Lord Protector and his Council, Is proved to be of DIVINE INSTITUTION; AND The great Stumbling-block of thouſands of Chriſtians (in regard of his Title) removed; proving it to be none other than what hath been given to thoſe whom God hath made inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental for his Peoples Deliverance of old.</p>
            <p>Written to ſatisfie unſatisfied Conſciences, By JOHN MOORE, a well-wiſher to the peace of our Engliſh <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>—Pray for the peace of Jeruſalem—Peace be within thy walls.—For my brethren and companions ſake, I will now ſay, Peace be within thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>—Thus ſaith the Lord, I will reſtore unto thee Judges as at firſt, and Counſellors as at the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>Henry Fletcher,</hi> at the three Cups in <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard, neer the Weſt-end. 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="invocation">
            <pb facs="tcp:118011:2"/>
            <head>The Author's Addreſs to God, before he put Pen to Paper, to write the enſuing Lines.</head>
            <l>GReat God of heav'n, thou God of Truth, do thou my thoughts direct,</l>
            <l>That I may write but what is right, of Him who doth protect</l>
            <l>(Subordinately to thy ſelf) this Land wherein I live:</l>
            <l>A ſpirit of Diſcerning, Lord, do thou unto me give;</l>
            <l>That I may clearly apprehend thy minde in this great Change,</l>
            <l>And from thy minde and will therein, let not my ſpirit range.</l>
            <l>Let no contempt of him that rules harbour within my breſt,</l>
            <l>Since under him, through providence, tranquillity and reſt,</l>
            <l>And peace for tender Conſcience is ratifi'd by Law;</l>
            <l>A priviledge of Liberty which <hi>England</hi> ſcarce ere ſaw.</l>
            <l>Let every tender Conſcience be ſatisfi'd likewiſe;</l>
            <l>Yea, ſuch a Liberty Lord grant, that all of us may prize;</l>
            <l>And from our very hearts and mindes acknowledge 't from above,</l>
            <l>And own it as a ſpecial Pledge and Emblem of thy love;</l>
            <l>That thou haſt giv'n us one to rule, whoſe ſoul deſires the good</l>
            <l>Of all thy ſervants in this Land, who for the Truth have ſtood.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118011:2"/>
            <head>To his Highneſs OLIVER By the Providence of God, Lord Protector of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Dominions thereunto belonging: J. M. <hi>wiſheth length of days with Peace and Safety here; and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life with Chriſt in glory here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith the poor widow, I have put in my Mite into the Publike Treaſury of acknowledging the Lawfulneſs of ſubmitting to the preſent Government, in which the Eternal God hath inveſted Your Highneſs at this day. I have taken the boldneſs to preſent it to Your Highneſs, for theſe Reaſons:</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe, of all men, you are moſt concerned in it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:118011:3"/>
Secondly, becauſe, of all men, it belongs moſt to you, to patronize and protect the weak acknowledgements of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive affectionate Obedience.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that you may know that God is ſtill owning you, and working for you, not onely by his Providence, in protecting your Perſon againſt the ſecret Combinations of a common Enemy; but by the more immediate working of his Spirit, to the ſatisfying of the Conſciences of many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied ſervants of Chriſt, whether the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with its endowments, be of God or no; in which my own ſoul was very lately unſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that under your Protection and Patronization, it may bring forth ſome fruit of Satisfaction to the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of ſome others (though never ſo few) that are yet at enmity in their ſpirits againſt the Title and Dignity of the Government.</p>
            <p>I have preſented it to publike view, for this Reaſon:</p>
            <p>That the world may know, that I am neither afraid, nor aſham'd, to own, acknowledge, and confeſs, the good hand and providence of the God of heaven and earth, in exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Perſon to that Honour and Dignity, and placing you as his (hitherto) undaunted and unwearied Servant in ſubordination to himſelf, to ſit at the Helm of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as at this day. Where ſitting to govern, it is the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned deſire of my ſoul, for You, and thoſe Honourable men in Counſel with You, That the Spirit of Chriſt may be your Guide, the Power of Chriſt your Life-guard, the Laws and Ordinances of Chriſt the Baſis and Foundation of yours, the Glory of Chriſt your greateſt Aim, the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the Goſpel your greateſt Glory, the Flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it your chiefeſt Joy: That you neglect no oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of doing good, when Chriſt commands it to be done, and in your power to do it: That in all your Undertakings and Counſels, you may lay your ſelves open to the all-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eye of God; that ſo you may eſcape that Curſe, which the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> pronounceth againſt thoſe that <hi>ſeek deep</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118011:3"/>
               <hi>to hide their counſel from the Lord, and their works are in the dark, and they ſay, Who ſeeth us? and who knoweth us?</hi> Iſai. 29.15. That your Body may poſſeſs as reſolved a heart to keep touch with God, in performing Vows and Promiſes made to him, as there was in <hi>Jephthah,</hi> who was once a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and a ſubordinate Protector in the hand of God, of his people <hi>Iſrael</hi> from the hand of the children of <hi>Ammon;</hi> who having opened his mouth unto the Lord, was ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of his promiſe, that he parted with the deareſt thing he had in the world, his onely childe, for beſide her he had neither Son nor daughter. <hi>Judg.</hi> 11.30, 31, 34, 35.</p>
            <p>The further deſire of my ſoul for your Highneſs, is, That God would give you (not onely) a ſpirit of diſcerning, to ſee where injuſtice and iniquity doth yet remain and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue amongſt the people; but alſo a free and reſolved ſpirit to improve ſuch power as God hath put into your hand, for the ſpeedy reforming and purging of it out: That your Council-chamber may be free from evil Counſels, and falſe-hearted diſſembling Counſellors: That both your Highneſs and your Council may be of one heart and one minde, free from all manner of diſſention and diſcord; becauſe that</p>
            <q>
               <l>Concordiâ parvae res creſcunt,</l>
               <l>Diſcordiâ magnae dilabuntur.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That your Courtly Attendants may be men of upright and faithful hearts, fearing God, and hating Vice: That all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inferiour Officers, in their ſeveral places ſubject to the Power by which they act, may diſcharge their duties with care and conſcience, void of Diſſimulation and Hypocriſie; not from Fear, but Affection to the Government which they ſeem to own: That the Army and Navie may be at peace in themſelves, free from the leaſt Mutiny: That all unſatisfied Conſciences touching the Legality of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, may be ſatisfied: That all heart-burnings of the People againſt it, may be quenched, through their cauſleſs complainings in the ſtreets, of Tyranny and Oppreſſion.
<pb facs="tcp:118011:4"/>
And laſtly, That the God of heaven would more and more enrich your Valiant heart with all ſuch endowments of Grace, Wiſdom, and Vertue, as becomes the minde and perſon of a Chriſtian Potentate, is and ſhall be the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſs moſt affectionate Servant, upon all juſt Commands, <hi>John Moore,</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118011:4"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Readers.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Friends, (if I may call you ſo)</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Dare be bold, many of you will admire and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (eſpecially thoſe of you to whom I am known) at this my publike Testimony of affectionate Loyalty to the preſent Government, having hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſcarcely given the leaſt ſolid Teſtimony of it: for I muſt confeſs, at the firſt appearance of it, I was (as many thouſands beſide) troubled in my minde, and unſatisfied in my conſcience concerning it; and the reaſon why, (as I now apprehend) was, becauſe (according to the determinate counſel of God, who worketh all things after the counſel of his own will) it was brought forth and eſtabliſhed, before it was ſo much as thought of; ſo that the ſudden appearance of it, did ſtartle many thouſands of tender-hearted Christians, lest Chriſt thereby ſhould loſe his honour and glory: out of which tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the honour of Chriſt, many dear ſervants of God, without deliberate conſideration, or without waiting to know the minde of God in ſuch a Change; did preſently, raſhly, and (in my appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion) unadviſedly, give publike teſtimony of the diſlike of their ſpirits to the Government, and the enmity of their hearts to the Perſon to whom God hath given it.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, the Common Enemy (although before, utterly van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed in the Field) ſeeing his dear Friends and Companions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their open enmity againſt him, and their diſlike of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, do take to themſelves freſh Courage, and re-animate themſelves, to plot and contrive his death, who had ſo many times jeoparded his life, for the peace and ſafety of his new declared <note n="*" place="margin">Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented Friends.</note> Enemies; nor is it unknown to <hi>England,</hi> that at length it brake forth into an open Hoſtile Inſurrection, which if it had taken effect, what could thoſe his diſcontented friends have expected,
<pb facs="tcp:118011:5"/>
but the utter ruine of themſelves and their Families<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute undoing, yea beggery, of all their innocent friends in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> for their diſlike of the preſent Government would not have quit them of their former enmity againſt the Royal party of the Kings Army, unleſs they would (as others had done before them) return to their vomit.</p>
            <p>But by this time, me thinks I hear ſome Reader ſay, that I have wrote this Teſtimony of my affection to the Government eſtabliſhed in the Protector and his Council, for ſome by-ends and ſelf-reſpects, and not from a real ſatisfaction of Conſcience. I do therefore give ſuch to know, that I take God to witneſs, who knows the ſecrets of all hearts, and as I believe I ſhall one day ſtand before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt, to give an account of my faith, and all deeds done in the fleſh from thence, That it is from a fully-ſatisfied Conſcience, of the lawfulneſs of ſubmitting to it, and from a full reſolution to the utmoſt of my power to own it, ſo far as it hath hitherto declared it ſelf, yea, though it be to the laying down of my life, which with his Higneſs, to whom God hath given the Power, I have heretofore been free and willing to do: having ſtill, (as I have alwayes had, ſince I had the leaſt knowledge of the worth of Chriſtian Liberty) this Motto upon the Shield of my minde:</p>
            <q>Praeſtat emori per Virtutem, quam per Dedecus vivere.</q>
            <p>Eſteeming it a thouſand times better to reſign my Heart-blood for the Teſtimony of my Conſcience, at the feet of an Enemy, than to live in contempt and diſgrace in obedience to his will. The ſame reſolution I finde to be in <hi>Sampſon,</hi> (although I am a worm and nothing in compariſon of him) who, rather than he would live in diſgrace to the Philiſtines, (whoſe profeſſed Enemy he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been) and be a laughing ſtock to them; he deſired of God, that he might die with them: a remarkable pattern, and worthy of a ſerious ſurvey of all Engliſh godly men, (and elſe) that have openly engaged againſt the late King and his party; that if we (through our own diviſions and diſſatisfaction one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) ſhould ſuffer a vanquiſhed Enemy to break in upon us, it
<pb facs="tcp:118011:5"/>
would fare full as evil with us as it did with <hi>Sampſon:</hi> all that we have would ſoon be taken from us, the eyes of our comfort would ſoon be put out, and we ſhould ſee that Freedom and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty that we have in the Goſpel no more, our conſciences bound to all their impoſitions with brazen Fetters, and be forced to grinde in the Mill of their cruelty; not a bit of bread ſhould we eat, but with ſorrow of heart: our lives would be bitter to us; yea, our lives would be a heavy burthen to us: every one of us from the higheſt to the loweſt, would be a <hi>Sampſon</hi> to make them ſport and paſtime, and the main Petition of our Prayer to God would be for death.</p>
            <p>So that there is no way left us viſibly appearing to eſcape theſe things, but to retain the ſtrength of affection to the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; under which, we ſit down under our Vines and Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees of ſpiritual freedom, and none to make us afraid.</p>
            <p>Now Reader, whoever thou art that haſt formerly engaged with him whom God hath exalted to the Supreme place of Civil Government in ſubjection to himſelf over the three Nations of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and yet canſt not fully cloſe with him in it, nor art ſatisfied in thy conſcience whether thou mayeſt lawfully do it; If the Teſtimony of the Word of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in Scripture eſpecially, or if Reaſon will ſatisfie thee, I have here preſented thee with both; by which I my ſelf was convinced, and my conſcience ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>If it be the change of the Government it ſelf, conſider, that ſuch an extraordinary and unheard-of change of Government in a Chriſtian Nation, could not have been, but by the ſpecial hand and determinate counſel of God, who worketh all things after the counſel of his own will.</p>
            <p>Secondly, is it the exaltation of his perſon, from a low eſtate, to ſuch a height of greatneſs and honour, that is a ſtumbling in thy way of affection? conſider what the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 75.6.7. <hi>Promotion comes neither from the Eaſt, nor from the Weſt, nor from the South: but God is the Judge; he putteth down one, and ſetteth up another.</hi> Compared with 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 7, 8. <hi>The Lord maketh poor, and maketh rich;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118011:6"/>
               <hi>he bringeth low, and lifteth up; he raiſeth up the poor out of the duſt, and lifteth up the begger from the dung-hill, to ſet them among Princes, and to make them inherit the Throne of Glory: for the pillars of the earth are the Lord's, and he hath ſet the world upon them.</hi> But I pray thee, without prejudice of Spirit, or hatred of Heart to his perſon whom God hath exalted amongſt us, Conſider the perſons whom God hath of old exalted over his people for their protection and ſafety. What honour and glory did God exalt <hi>Joſeph</hi> to, whoſe Father <hi>Jacob</hi> was but a Shepherd? <hi>Moſes</hi> was a poor Shepherd, yet choſen of God to be a Governour of his own people. <hi>Joſhua</hi> the Son of a poor Iſraelite, and a Servant of <hi>Moſes,</hi> after his death had the command of Government over the people; becauſe he followed the Lord fully: and the Lord emboldned him with a couragious heart, that he did animate the Captains that were with him, to tread upon the necks of five Kings; ſaying, <hi>Come neer, put your feet upon the necks of them. And Joſhua ſaid unto them, Fear not, nor be diſmayed, be ſtrong and of good courage; for thus ſhall the Lord do to all your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies againſt whom ye fight.</hi> After the death of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> the people fell away from following the Lord, and the Lord af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted them by the hands of the Midianites. And they cried unto the Lord, who for his Names ſake appointed <hi>Gideon</hi> to be their Protector from the ſpoil of the Midianites: who being but of a mean Family in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſpake thus unto the Angel of the Lord: <hi>O my Lord, wherewith ſhall I ſave Iſrael? behold, my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily is poor in Manaſſeth, and I the leaſt in my Father's houſe. And the Lord ſaid unto him, Surely I will be with thee, and thou ſhalt ſmite the Midianites as one man.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of <hi>Gideon,</hi> in their diſtreſs he gave them <hi>Jephtha,</hi> one of a ſmall reckoning amongſt them in their proſperity. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Jephtha, Sampſon</hi> was given them to be their Deliverer from the hands of the Philiſtines. Thus did God of old appoint men of his own chuſing, to be Head in the Government of his people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and furniſhed them with parts ſuitable thereto; and raiſed them from a low eſtate to honour and renown.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, is it the Title of Protector, that thou ſtumbleſt at?
<pb facs="tcp:118011:6"/>
then conſider, that the Title of Protector was a Title given to the Governours of <hi>Iſrael</hi> long before they had a King to reign over them: for I will ask thee this ſingle Queſtion, What difference there is between a <hi>Protector</hi> and a <hi>Saviour.</hi> I finde then in Scripture, that this Title of Saviour God hath formerly conferr'd upon thoſe Worthies that have been faithful Inſtruments in his hand to go in and out before his people againſt his and their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: which Title <hi>Nehemiah</hi> acknowledgeth; <hi>chap.</hi> 9. 27. <hi>Therefore thou deliveredſt them into the hands of their enemies, who vexed them; and in the time of their trouble they cried unto thee, thou heardſt them from heaven, and according to thy manifold mercies thou gaveſt them a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, who ſaved them out of the hand of their enemies.</hi> And this Title I clearly apprehend ſhall continue to thoſe that ſhall be for the time to come inſtrumental in the hand of God for the ſafety of his people; God having promiſed by the Prophet <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiah,</hi> That he will reſtore to his people Judges as at firſt, and their Counſellors as at the beginning, that <hi>Zion</hi> ſhall be redeemed with judgement, and her converts with righteouſneſs; and the Title that they ſhall have at that time, when ſuch deliverance ſhall be wrought, ſhall be Saviours or Protectors, there being no difference as I know between Salvation and Protection: and that this ſhall be the Title of honour which God will give to ſuch (a better name than that of Sons) read the laſt Verſe of the Prophet <hi>Obadiah,</hi> where it is thus written: <hi>And Saviours ſhall come up on Mount Zion, to judge the Mount of Eſau, and the Kingdoms ſhall be the Lord's.</hi> But becauſe I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſomewhat more of my minde concerning theſe and other Scriptures of like nature, in the enſuing Treatiſe; I ſhall refer thee to it for thy further ſatisfaction; deſiring, that thy judgment may not be blinded by thy own will: which if it be not, I hope thou wilt have as much ſatisfaction in reading it, as I had in writing it; which is the main deſire of </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>him who unfeignedly deſireth the Peace and Welfare of his Country,</hi> J. Moore.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_fellow_sectarians">
            <pb facs="tcp:118011:7"/>
            <head>A Word to the Servants of Chriſt in Covenant with him through Grace, and in fellowſhip together under the Ordinances of the Goſpel.</head>
            <p>I Do wonder and admire that ſo few of you have given pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Teſtimony of your affection to the preſent Government, eſtabliſhed amongſt us through the providence of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; which makes me conceive it hath an ill ſavour amongſt you, or out of a tenderneſs of Conſcience to the exaltation of Chriſt's Kingdom, and longing for his reign, you cannot fully cloſe with it. Now I beſeech you Brethren, (from the tender love of my Soul to the Peace and Welfare of your Souls and Bodies) that you will without prejudicate thoughts weigh theſe two or three Conſiderations in the balance of your Spirits.</p>
            <p>Firſt, conſider, That the chiefeſt ground of all our Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Watchfulneſs, Wearineſs, Painfulneſs, the ſhedding of our own and friends deareſt Blood; yea, the Prayers and Tears that have been offered before the Lord in your ſeveral Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, hath been for the full Enjoyment of Freedom and Liberty in the ſervice of Chriſt, from the coercive compulſions of bloody, perſecuting, penal Statutes<hi>:</hi> and now it is granted both from God, and by Oath from his Highneſs the Lord Protector to the utmoſt of his power to be protected in it (as if we were already weary of it) we hate the Inſtrument by which it is confirmed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, conſider the frame of your own Spirits at preſent, with what they once were, when ſuch Freedom and Liberty was precious to you: would you not once have owned almoſt any
<pb facs="tcp:118011:7"/>
civil Government that would have granted that ſpiritual Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which we now enjoy? I dare be bold, that if the late King had proclaimed ſuch Liberty to his Subjects, he had been alive to this day, except ſickneſs had cut him off; and that the people of God in <hi>England,</hi> formerly called by the name of Puritans, to whom ſuch Freedom was precious, would have laid their Bodies and Eſtates at his feet, to manifeſt their affection. And pray you, what is the reaſon that we are ſo dull, ſo dead, and ſo void of our publick manifeſtation of affection to him, that with the often hazarding his life hath been made inſtrumental in the hand of God to purchaſe it for us? yea, we are ſo far from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring our affection, that a great part of us ſwell with hatred towards him; an evil requital for his labour of love towards us: for if you well conſider how many fell away to the Enemy, and ſought our deſtruction; and others that had been admirable Inſtruments for a ſeaſon, threw up their Commiſſions, refuſing to act any further; and how he, (I mean the Lord Protector that now is) never refuſed to act for that Freedom we now enjoy; but like another <hi>Joſhua</hi> or <hi>Caleb</hi> followed the Lord fully in the work that he was called to, and left us not till we had enjoyed that Liberty in the Goſpel that we long looked for, (except we are blinde, and can't ſee when good cometh:) I ſay, If we conſider theſe things, we have not the leaſt cauſe to manifeſt the leaſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affection, either to the Government, or the Perſon to whom it is given; but contrariwiſe, hearty affection, with all cheerfulneſs that we can.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Meaſure the diſpoſition of your Spirits with the Saints in the primitive times of the Goſpel, and you'l finde, that ſuch peaceable Liberty which we enjoy under the preſent Government, was of ſuch worth to them, that they could pray for Kings, and all that were in Authority, that under them they might lead a peaceable and a quiet life: and acknowledge, that the Powers that were, were ordained of God; although at that time they were generally Enemies to Chriſt, and Perſecutors of his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. And lo, we are ſo different in our Spirits, from the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications of theirs, that we cannot own that power to be of God, that hath made proviſion for the peace and tranquillity of
<pb facs="tcp:118011:8"/>
the ſervants of Chriſt, in the Freedom of their Conſciences, and is tender of their welfare.</p>
            <p>Now I beſeech you dear Friends, if Freedom and Liberty in the ſervice of Chriſt be of any account with you; be not ſullen in your Spirits, put away that peeviſhneſs of heart that is yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in any of you againſt the Government eſtabiſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us: ſay not, That is not of God, that is a furtherance to, and a countenancer of godlineſs: call not that your Enemy, which hath vowed your Protection: let's not ſay to him that hath ſtood to the face of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> for us, <hi>Who made thee a Judge and Ruler over us?</hi> as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did to <hi>Moſes.</hi> But let us u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimouſly cloſe with and own him, that hath ſo cheerfully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged for our ſafety, when others left us: for in all probability, our murmuring and repining at his exaltation, may continue freſh plottings and contrivings of the common Enemy to take away his life; and from thence foſter their hopes of enſlaving us again.</p>
            <p>Now that you may conſider theſe things with an equal hand, for the preventing of your own ruine, and the loſs of the moſt precious Liberty in the World; and, that the Lord would open the Eyes of our Judgements, that you may ſee where you are, is the unfeigned deſire of him, who deſires to commend himſelf to every one of your Conſciences in the things preſented to you, and remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your poor Friend, and unworthy Fellow-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant in the Bonds of Peace, J. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118011:8"/>
            <head>Protection proclaimed, <hi>&amp;c. The preſent Government eſtabliſhed in the three Nations of</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>&amp;c. is of God.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE great Creator of Heaven and Earth, who by his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſupporteth the whole Creation, hath made of one Blood all Nations of Men, for to dwell on the earth, and hath determined the times appointed, and the bounds of their Habitation; even he that worketh all things after the counſel of his own will, though man know it not, and perceive it not; without whom there is not a ſparrow falls to the ground, nor the hair from a man's head; who hath bounded and limited all his Creatures, ſo that their bounds and limits they cannot paſs without him: the Sun, and Moon, and Stars in their conſtant courſe are ſubſervient to his will, the Sea keeps its bounds at the command of the Almighty; yea, every little Water courſe obſerves its Makers will: the ſame God by his determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate counſel, hath bounded and limited the ſons of men, both in their habitations and power, beyond which they cannot paſs; <hi>Moſes</hi> the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of the Lord witneſſeth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.7, 8. ſaying, <hi>Remember the dayes of old, conſider the years of many generations, ask thy Father and he will ſhew thee, when the moſt high divided to the Nations their inheritance, when he ſeparated the ſons of Adam, he ſet the bounds of the people according to the number of the children of Iſrael.</hi> The ſame God, the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever, by the ſame power will, and counſel, hath bounded, limited, and put an end to the power and reign of the <hi>Norman</hi> Race of Kings and Queens in <hi>England;</hi> yea, the time of the late Parliaments Government was limited by God. So that let them all be diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented never ſo much, fret, chafe, and rage; yea, nil they, will they, they muſt ſtoop to the determinate counſel of Jehovah's will: ſo that by the Divine inſtitution of him, who hath wrought all theſe things af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the counſel of his own will, is the preſent Government eſtabliſhed in <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> (ſubordinately to God) the entituled Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector thereof; and whoſoever he be that denies it, or ſpeaks againſt it,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118011:9"/>
denies the Omniregency of God, and the Ordinance of his will: for the Scripture ſaith, That <hi>promotion cometh neither from the eaſt, nor from the weſt, nor from the ſouth: but God is the Judge; he putteth down one, and ſetteth up another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for further ſatisfaction, (to my Country in general, &amp; in particular to all thoſe that have heretofore engaged for that Liberty we now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy) that the preſent Government eſtabliſhed in his Highneſs and his Council, is of God, I have inſerted theſe Arguments following.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that Government and Rule that anſwers the main deſire and requeſt of God for his people, muſt needs be of God. Now if it be proved, that this Government is correſpondent to the main requeſt and deſire of God for his people on earth, then it muſt be of God: and that it doth ſo, I prove it thus:</p>
            <p>God's main deſire for his people on earth is, That the powers below touch not his Anointed, and do his Prophets no harm; but, that they may ſerve him without fear, in holineſs and righteouſneſs all the days of their life.</p>
            <p>Now this Government hath anſwered the deſire of God herein, and hath made proviſion for their peace and ſafety, and hath vowed their protection: ſo that they may without fear of any penal, bloody, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Law, worſhip him in the adminiſtration of the Goſpel with Freedom and Liberty, without confines of time or place.</p>
            <p>Therefore of God.</p>
            <p>God hath promiſed by his ſervant <hi>Obadiah</hi> the Prophet, That Saviours ſhall come up on Mount <hi>Sion</hi> to judge the Mount of <hi>Eſau;</hi> yea, this I ſay, that ſuch ſhall come, and one is, that ſhall judge, condemn, and throw down the Mount of <hi>Eſau. Eſau</hi> was a Perſecutor of his Brother <hi>Jacob,</hi> becauſe he had obtained the bleſſing of ſpiritual things, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf went without them. Now by this Mount of <hi>Eſau,</hi> I underſtand the Mountainous Power of Perſecutors of the Servants of Chriſt for their Faith in him, which ſhall in due time be conſumed like ſtubble, and by degrees come to nought, by the hand of thoſe whom God ſhall ſend as Saviours for the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Object. I know that this will be objected: <hi>If this Government be ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the Freedom and Liberty of the Servants of Chriſt, why then are ſo many eminent Servants of Chriſt reſtrained in priſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, Although the Lord knows I have both in private and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick prayed for their deliverance, and that the difference between them and the Lord Protector (by whom they are impriſoned) may be reconciled; he to them in loving kindneſs and favour, and they to him by acknowledging the hand of God in exalting him to the Government in which he is inveſted: Yet I ſay, That they are not impriſoned as they are Servants of Chriſt, nor is it for their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118011:9"/>
Conſcience in the worſhip of Chriſt, in the Faith of the Goſpel, that they are reſtrained of Liberty: but for their diſcontent, diſlike, and diſſatisfaction towards him, and the Government which God hath put into his Hand: and for my part, I think it no indiſcretion nor cruelty for any man to tie down (for a time) that hand that cannot hold ſtill, but muſt be ſcratching at his body till it bleed, and ſo endanger the whole to deſtruction: <hi>caetera mitto loqui;</hi> leſt any ſhould think that I either wiſh or deſire their reſtraint from their Liberty, which the Lord knows I do not, but from my very Soul deſire their enjoyment of it; ſo that it may ſtand with the peace and preſervation of the whole body.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider that the wayes and workings of God, eſpecially in things of ſuch great concernment as the Rule and Government of his people, do not anſwer the expectation, thoughts, nor will of man. I know, that if this Nation had been divided into ten parts, nine of them would have had the yoke of the Norman Race to have continued: if there had been one part of ten left, nine parts of that one, would have ſubjected themſelves to the yoke of a Parliamentary Government; now that God might croſs the expectation of man, and let us know, that our thoughts herein were vain, he did upon a ſuddain bring forth and eſtabliſh ſuch a Government that we leaſt thought of; that leſs of Man, and more of God might be ſeen in it.</p>
            <p>When the time of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Reign over <hi>Iſrael</hi> in God's Decree was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, he commanded the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> to leave off grieving for <hi>Saul;</hi> telling him, That he had rejected him for being King over his people; and told him, That he had provided for himſelf a King amongſt the Sons of <hi>Jeſſe</hi> the <hi>Bethlemite,</hi> one that was not ſo much as thought of, (in regard of ruling over them for the future) not in all <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The Prophet at firſt was afraid to go, for fear of <hi>Saul,</hi> that he would kill him; but at laſt he did go: and when he came and beheld his Sons, he found the ſecret will of God clean contrary to his thoughts and purpoſe: for when he beheld <hi>Eliab,</hi> he thought him to be moſt likely, and did pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to anoint him for a future Governour of the people; but the Lord ſaid unto <hi>Samuel,</hi> Look not on his countenance, nor on the hight of his ſtature, becauſe I have refuſed him; for the Lord ſeeth not as Man ſeeth; for Man looketh on the outward appearance, but the Lord looketh on the heart; and the moſt unlikely to carnal apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, did God make choice of to be the Governour of his people, and by his Decree anointed him in Spirit for the ſame end, long before he came to the Government.</p>
            <p>And truely for my part I do confidently believe from my very Soul, that from the beginning of theſe late Wars, the Lord did ſecretly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, and in his own purpoſe ſet apart <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> (our intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Lord Protector) to be the head Governour, below himſelf, of all the people in the three Nations; Although at the beginning of theſe late Wars, it was as unlikely for him to be Lord Protector of three Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118011:10"/>
in the judgement of man, as it was for <hi>David</hi> (in the apprehenſion of his Father and Brethren) to be Ruler over <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But let all the Servants of God know; yea, let every individual Soul in the three Nations know, That the counſel and determinate purpoſe of God will ſtand as an irreſiſtable prick againſt all that ſpurn at it, and a ſharp thorn in the ſides of all his enemies. For as the Heavens are higher than the Earth; ſo are the wayes and counſels of God higher than the wayes and counſels of Men, and his thoughts tranſcending theirs. What earthly powers, what plottings and contrivings of an Enemy, what ragings, ſwellings, tumults of vanquiſhed Foes, what murmurings repinings, or diſcontents of any people, ſhall reverſe the thing that God hath purpoſed to bring to paſs? God is not a Man, that he ſhould lye, neither the Son of Man, that he ſhould repent: hath he ſaid it, and ſhall he not do it? or hath he ſpoken, and ſhall he not make it good? for whatſoever the Lord pleaſeth, that doth he in Heaven and in Earth, and in all places.</p>
            <p>This therefore ſhall henceforth be the Petition of my Soul, <hi>Thy will be done in earth as it is in heaven: Let God make haſte to compleat his purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This alſo ſhall be my Souls melody, which I will ſing with a joyful noiſe in my heart, <hi>Bleſſed be the name of the Lord from this time forth and for evermore: From the riſing of the Sun, to the going down of the ſame, the Lords name is to be praiſed. The Lord is high above all Nations, and his glory above the Heavens. Who is like unto the Lord our God, who dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth on high? Who humbleth himſelf to behold the things that are done in Heaven and Earth. He raiſeth up the poor out of the duſt, and lifteth the needy out of the dunghil, that he may ſet him with Princes, even with the Princes of his people,</hi> Amen, Hallelujah.</p>
            <p>That Government that gives Chriſt the chiefeſt honour due unto him, is of God.</p>
            <p>The greateſt honour that belongs to Chriſt here below, is, That he may bear Rule without interruption in the hearts and conſciences of his Servants:</p>
            <p>If this Government then do leave the power over the conſciences of the Servants of Chriſt ſolely to him, then it is of God.</p>
            <p>But this Government doth ſo:</p>
            <p>Therefore of God.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay no more to this firſt thing, namely, That the Government is of God, until occaſion of reply (which I look for) doth engage me to it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As the Government is of God, ſo there is none more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving to ſit at the helm of it (in ſubordination to God) then <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> the preſent intituled Lord Protector.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if conſtant, faithful, unwearied, undaunted Service, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with Magnanimity, Valour and Courage, for the Liberty and Freedom of the people of God in <hi>England,</hi> from the bloody and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118011:10"/>
Statutes and Laws do deſerve it, then doth he deſerve it: his Conſtancy hath appeared, in that he was in continual ſervice day and night. His Faithfulneſs, in that he never betrayed the leaſt of his Truſt, but proved from firſt to laſt, as true as ſteel to his Country. His Unweariedneſs, in holding up his hand by Commiſſion, when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers let theirs fall; for if he had threw up his Commiſſion when others did theirs, when the Scots twice invaded us with a numerous Army, I believe we had been in a miſerable condition before now. His Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauntedneſs hath the whole Army ſeen: he was never known to decline action, although the advantage have been never ſo great againſt him; for the moſt part, if not alwayes, charging in the Front of his Army, againſt the moſt reſolved Enemy; and ſeldom, or never did he retreat without Victory.</p>
            <p>I have heard with my own Ears, ſome gallant Sparks of the Cavalry ſay; That he was the moſt gallant reſolved General that ever drew Sword in Chriſtendom, ſince the time of <hi>Scanderbeg;</hi> and, that if it were againſt a Forrain Nation, they would as faithfully and as cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſerve under his Command, as under any one in the world: And that at laſt the very name of him was ſuch a terror to them, that they could not force on their Men to fight, if they knew he was in the Field.</p>
            <p>A valiant and a couragious General ſtrikes terror to the heart of an Enemy, although the number on his party be but few. The very name of <hi>Gideon</hi> ſtruck terror into the hearts of the Midianites that lay as Graſhoppers for multitude; yea, at the very report of the Sword of the Lord and of <hi>Gideon,</hi> they fled and were diſcomfited, though he had but three hundred men with him.</p>
            <p>The Proweſs and gallant Atchievments of the Army (ſince he was their Head in chief) in bringing to ſubjection a potent enemy in three Kingdoms, and ſetling them in peace and quietneſs, (except a few hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpurs that bit their tongues with the very anguiſh of their ſpirits againſt him; and clandeſtinely making a pit for his life, they fell into it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) hath made all the Nations ſtand amazed with admiration. His Underſtanding and Judgement both in religious and civil affairs, is acute and ſharp; whereby he is able to judge the differences of the one, and with wonderful policy to act in the other for the protection and ſafety (in civil affairs) of the three Nations.</p>
            <p>Therefore laying aſide all envy, heart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>burnings, diſlike, contempt, hatred, enmity, meditations of diviſion, murmurings, repinings, grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, at the Government, and at the honourable Exaltation of the Perſon who (in ſubmiſſion to God) is dignified with the Titie of Lord Protector, it behoves all the good people of the three Nations, cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and cordially to ſubmit unto it, and acknowledge it a Mercy that God hath placed ſuch an one over them, that hath been a chief inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his hand, an invaluable Liberty to purchaſe for them; and is tender and careful of the continuance of it: for, for my own part, I
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118011:11"/>
look upon it as one of the greateſt mercies that ever <hi>England</hi> enjoyed, and that it behoves all the faithful in the three Nations to ſubmit unto it, let them conſider theſe things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Seeing that if there muſt be a Government till Chriſt ſhall come, let ſuch a Government be acknowledg'd that comes neareſt to Chriſt: and truely for my part it is clear to me, that this Government now eſtabliſhed, comes nearer to Chriſt, (for reaſons before alledg'd) then any that I have read of ſince Chriſts incarnation; whoſe coming is prepared as the morning, which breaketh forth clearer and clearer to the perfect day: Let us not then be angry at the Sun, becauſe it is not in the height of the Firmment, ſo ſoon as the day breakes; but let's wait upon God as he moves in exaltation, for he that believes will not make haſte; learn what that means, and be not like the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of old, who fell out with <hi>Moſes,</hi> becauſe they did not preſently enjoy the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which he had promiſed them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, conſider that there can be no breach made againſt this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, but by Civil diſcord and bloody diviſion amongſt our ſelves; and except we delight in embruing our hands in one anothers blood, we will not hearken to any Seditious Principle. And I beſeech you, dear Friends and Country-men, lay to heart the miſerable deſolation of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> who though they were exceeding ſtrong, and Victorious againſt an enemy, whileſt they were united; yet what bloody ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and unheard-of maſſacres were wrought amongſt them, by the civil diſcord of Seditious Captains, and their ſiding one againſt another! tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly my very heart hath bled within me to read of it. What ruine and miſery did the ſeditious diſcord of <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and thoſe two hundred &amp; fifty Princes of the congregation that came to <hi>Moſes</hi> and told him that he took too much upon him to rule over them! the earth opened her mouth and ſwallowed up part of them; and fourten thouſand ſeven hundred were conſumed by a noyſon Plague: which ſhews the great wrath of God revealed from heaven againſt ſeditious principles amongſt his own people, quarreling at that Government and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour whom he had placed over them. Now I beſeech you, if you would not have your Country made an Akeldama, nor the channells of your Cities and Towns run down with blood; if you would not ſee your Wives and Daughters raviſh'd before your faces, and the brains of your little ones daſhed againſt the walls: if you would not hear your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren cry to you for a bit of bread when you have none to give them, and your ſelves ſtagger and reel in the ſtreets for want of bread to ſupport you feeble bodies? would you not be drag'd by the hair of the head from your ſeveral meetings in the worſhip of God? would you not have your blood mixt with your Prayers? would you not have the eyes of all your comforts put out? would you not grinde in the mill of a cruel enemy? if you love your lives and liberties, or any thing that is dear; if you value chriſtian liberty at any price; if you count it worth any thing, let no prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118011:11"/>
of ſedition againſt the preſent Government be entertained amongſt you, leaſt you repent it when it is too late.</p>
            <p>There is no other way left to the enemy, for to break in upon us, but our own ſedition and diviſions; conſider how forward the Devil hath been in all ages to blow with his mouth at ſuch a coale, and what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable flames he hath blown them to; 'tis that the enemy ſtands gaping for, you cannot do them a greater pleaſure; how do they laugh in their ſleeves when they hear of ſuch a thing! 'Tis Nuts for them, you cannot offer them a greater preſent, 'twill make them more paſtime then all the Play-houſes in <hi>London:</hi> Remember how the Lords of the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines</hi> ſent for <hi>Sampſon</hi> to make them ſport; the Nations that are round about us that are our enemies, they hate us already with a bitter hatred, and wait for an opportunity to do us any miſchief they can: this way they hope to breake in upon us, even our diſaffection to the Government, and diviſions amongſt our ſelves; if you think it cannot be, why <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> thought the ſame, yea their enemies thought ſo too: <hi>Jeremiah</hi> in his <hi>Lamentations,</hi> breaks forth into theſe words: <hi>The Kings of the earth, and all the inhabitants of the world, would not have believed, that the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary and the enemy ſhould have entred into the gates of Jeruſalem.</hi> Lam. 4. 12.</p>
            <p>Let us fruſtrate all their hopes then, of bringing us into a two-fold ſlavery, of conſcience, and body, by a reſolvedneſs of heart to ſubmit unto that Government, under which we enjoy unſpeakable liberty; conſidering that in the deſtruction of it, lyeth our abſolute ruine and miſery: For I muſt tell you, whoſoever you be, that cannot ſee it, and own it to be of God, ye are either as a common enemy poſſeſt with deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate envy, or elſe as ſeeming friends with raſh judgement of blind zeal. But for my own part I am ſatisfied in this one thing, that there have been very few in former ages (if any at all) whom God hath made choice of, and by providence kept and preſerved, to Rule over his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but ſome of their friends have either enviouſly maglign'd them, or elſe clandeſtinely ſought their harm. <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſpeaks to his brethren, of God's exalting him above them; and they preſently conſpire his death. <hi>Moſes</hi> (although he had oftentimes endangered his life before <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> for the Iſraelites, and was inſtrumental in the hand of God for their freedom; yet) could ſcarcely get a good word from many of them: they could ask him, <hi>Who made him a Ruler and a Judge over them?</hi> And <hi>Corah</hi> and his confederates could tell him to his face, that <hi>he took too much upon him,</hi> they were as good as he. It is written of them in the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> that it did proceed from envie: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.16. <hi>They envied Moſes alſo in the Camp, and Aaron the Saint of the Lord. Gideon</hi> found but ſmall kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at their hands, for all his ſervice done for their ſafety; So that <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im</hi> chid him very ſharply: the like requitall had <hi>Jephtha</hi> from <hi>Epbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im;</hi> becauſe he did not acquaint them with his proceedings, they threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to burn his houſe over his head: <hi>Sampſons</hi> friends for his ſervice,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118011:12"/>
could binde him and deliver him to the <hi>Philiſtines:</hi> how often was <hi>Sauls</hi> Javelin caſt at <hi>David</hi> enviouſly, becauſe the Lord was with him, and had exalted him into the peoples affection and love?</p>
            <p>So that its no marvail though he whom God hath made inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal for the peace and tranquillity of his people in <hi>England,</hi> do meet with the like ingratitude from ſome of them. I have obſerved this for a real truth, that if envy do fancy evil in a good man, it will both write and ſpeak againſt him, as if he were the vileſt man alive; becauſe it is both blind, and is ſuch a paſſion that will have no pacification,</p>
            <p>Did ever any Generall in this world, engage for a people, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Victory, but he was made Ruler over them? <q>Would not a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin if ſhe be forcibly raviſhed againſt her will, and ſhould be delivered out of the raviſhers hand by ſome other man?</q> Would ſhe not all the dayes of her life, love, and honour and reſpect the reſcuer? ſure I think ſhe would, or elſe ſhe were very ungrateful.</p>
            <p>Is not the conſcience more pure then the body? the defilement of the body is nothing to the pollution of the conſcience; the raviſhment of the body is nothing to the forcing of the conſcience.</p>
            <p>If then he hath ſtood up faithfully and ſtoutly, to reſcue us from the bloody penall perſecuting Lawes of Tyranny over the conſcience; if we do not all the dayes of our lives, love, honour and reſpect him, we are as ungrateful a people both to God and to him the inſtrument in chief as ever were in the world, and cannot in conſcience deſire any good from him. But the reaſons (as I apprehened) why ſo many Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans zealouſly profeſſing Chriſt, are unſatisfied in their conſcience, at the eſtabliſhment of the Government, are theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the ſuddain appearance of it, contrary to their thoughts and expectations; becauſe their thoughts and mindes were contented and ſatisfied in the Government of a Parliament, not thinking in the leaſt, that God would have eſtabliſhed any other Government in the Nation; the appearance of ſuch a Government, which was directly contrary to their faith and premeditation of heart, ſtartles their Spirits, and fills them, not onely with doubt whether it be of God or no, but with abſolute perſwaſions, that it was not of God.</p>
            <p>Now then, my dear Friends, I would ask you this ſingle Queſtion, <hi>If God will reſtore to his people, Judges as at the firſt, and Counſellors as at the beginning, then whether or no that the ancient Commonwealth of</hi> Iſrael <hi>was not governed by</hi> Moſes <hi>as a Protector, who alſo had Counſellors with him; by</hi> Joſhua, Gideon, Jephtha, <hi>and the reſt, before either Kings or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments?</hi> So that I cleerly ſee in the eſtabliſhment of this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the beginning of God's work in fulfilling his promiſe of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive reſtitution of Judges and Counſellors, as at the beginning, before they were governed either by Kings or Parliaments. All the Promiſes of God are yea, and <hi>Amen:</hi> Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away, but not one jot or tittle of the promiſes of the Lord, till all of them be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled. And I am ſure that's one.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:118011:12"/>
Let us take heed then of murmuring at the appearance of the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of God's promiſes, leſt God hide it from us again, as he did from the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> God having told <hi>Abraham</hi> above four hundred yeers before, That they ſhould be Strangers in a Land that was not theirs, and that they ſhould be afflicted four hundred yeers, and that afterwards he would bring them forth of it: the time being come that God would accompliſh his promiſe in his own ſecret will and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate counſel, he did purpoſe to make it good by the hand of <hi>Moſes;</hi> who, when he was full forty yeers old, God put it into his heart to viſit his Brethren, the Children of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and ſeeing one of them ſuffer wrong, he defended him, and avenged him that was oppreſſed, and ſmote the Egyptian: for he ſuppoſed, that his Brethren would have underſtood, how that God by his hand would deliver them; but they underſtood it not. And when he would have made peace betwixt two of his Brethren that were at ſtrife, one of them asked him, Who made thee a Ruler and a Judge over us? at this ſaying, <hi>Moſes</hi> fled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And forty yeers more affliction did God continue unto them for this one Murmurer. Let our Engliſh Iſraelites conſider this, and take heed of murmuring and repining at the good hand of God in giving us a faithful and a careful Governour of his peoples Liberty, leſt God withdraw his hand, and leave us and our children to a farther trial of Bondage.</p>
            <p>The ſecond I apprehend was and is this: they did not wait upon the Lord, nor ſeek unto him by prayer to know his minde and will in ſuch a ſudden Change: ſo that in ſtead of waiting upon God, and ſeeking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him by prayer to know his minde and will therein; ſuppoſing it not to be of God, becauſe it was contradictory to their thoughts and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation; they rather bent their mindes and ſtudies to finde out ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of corruption in it, that might make it appear not to be of God; and finding ſomething in it, which their Spirits did not diſreliſh, they could not be ſatisfied that it was of God: whereas I am confident, if they had waited upon God, and ſought unto him by Prayer, to know his minde and will in ſuch an extraordinary change, they had been ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, and could not but have ſeen it to be of God.</p>
            <p>A third Reaſon was: they were afraid, leſt way would have been made by it, for the induction and bringing in of ſuch falſe worſhips, as would embondage the free Spirits of the zealouſly godly people in the three Nations; whereas proviſion is made to the contrary, and their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection vowed; yea, and we ſhall enjoy it, if we do not wilfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive our<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſelves of it, and by our own diviſions make ourſelves a prey to our enemies: for that Proverb is certain true,</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whileſt the Bore and Lion ſtrives,</l>
                  <l>The Eagle waits for both their lives.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The meaning is, whilſt Friends contend,</l>
                  <l>Their Foes will ſpoil them in the end.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118011:13"/>
A fourth Reaſon was, Becauſe they were not made acquainted with it; and ſo like <hi>Ephraim,</hi> againſt <hi>Jephtha,</hi> they were diſpleaſed with him, though he had deſerved no ſuch thing at their hands.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, being formerly their equal, they took it ill (many of them) that he ſhould be exalted to rule over them: therefore many of them thought, and do ſtill think, that he hath taken too much upon him. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> and his Accomplices told <hi>Moſes</hi> as much; but the Holy Ghoſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth us to rejoyce, when a Brother of low degree is exalted: for ſuch a one is moſt fit for it, eſpecially being endowed with ſutable qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as none alive I think can deny, but that our preſent Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector is, and as prudent Counſellors for his Aſſiſtants. So that in ſuch a Government, and ſuch Governours to manage it; let all the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected people of the three Nations rejoyce, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
